Guide to the Birmingham United Church of Christ Records, 1843-1977 AIS.1977.30
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Birmingham United Church of Christ Records
1843-1977
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Birmingham United Church of Christ (Pittsburgh, Pa.)
AIS.1977.30
10 microfilm_reels
The Birmingham United Church of Christ, originally chartered in June of 1846 as a United Evangelical Protestant Church, arose from the efforts of German-speaking residents living in the borough of Birmingham (now the South Side of Pittsburgh) who had worshipped at the Smithfield Street United Evangelical Protestant Church. The collection consists of ten reels of microfilm containing a constitution and journal, history, minute books, lists of members, memorial publications, baptismal, marriage, burial, and financial records from 1843-1977. Digital reproductions of the microfilm are available online.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the collection are available online.
History
The Birmingham United Church of Christ, originally chartered in June of 1846 as a United Evangelical Protestant Church, arose from the efforts of German-speaking residents living in the borough of Birmingham (now the South Side of Pittsburgh) who had worshipped at the Smithfield Street United Evangelical Protestant Church. Throughout its history, the word 'Birmingham' has been retained in identifying this church. In 1924, the Birmingham church joined other United Evangelical Protestant Churches in the General Council of Congregational Churches. In 1964, the churches affiliated with the United Church of Christ.
Scope and Content Notes
The Birmingham United Church of Christ Records consists of ten reels of microfilm containing a constitution and journal, history, minute books, lists of members, memorial publications, baptismal, marriage, burial, and financial records from 1843-1977. Also contained in the collection is a burial register that spans from 1902-1975 and cemetary deeds from 1896-1975. The church constitution and journal are in German and span from 1846-1889. The "official" church history dates from 1846-1926; there is also mention of an "unofficial" church history. The collection also has a 50th Year Jubilee Booklet, in German, that is dated 1896. The finanical records span from 1889-1967.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These records were microfilmed, with permission, by the Archives Service Center in 1977.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original records retained by Birmingham United Church of Christ, 25 Carrick Ave., Pittsburgh, PA 15210.
Previous Citation
Birmingham United Church of Christ Records, 1843-1977, AIS.1977.30, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Previously cited as two separate collections: Birmingham United Church of Christ, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1845-1976, AIS Micro 77:30a, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh; and, Birmingham United Church of Christ, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records, 1843-1977, AIS Micro 77:30b, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh Libraries
Marriage records; Minute books; Church records; Church buildings -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Burial records; Financial records; Churches and Synagogues; Baptismal records -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Confirmation records -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Church history; Birmingham United Church of Christ (Pittsburgh, Pa.); United Church of Christ -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh
- General Record Books, I.
  - General Records, 1845-1865 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Baptisms, 1845-1856; Part 1.
    - Confirmations, 1846-1861; Part 2.
    - Marriage & Death Records, 1846-1849; Part 3.
    - Deaths, 1850-1862; Part 4.
    - Baptisms, 1854-1858; Part 5.
    - Marriage Records, 1854-1862; Part 6.
    - Baptisms, 1858-1862; Part 7.
  - General Records, 1862-1898 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Baptisms, 1862-1869; Part 2.
    - Marriage Records, 1862-1869; Part 3.
    - Death/Burial Records, 1862-1869; Part 4.
    - Confirmation/Membership Statistics, 1870-1898; Part 5.
    - Confirmations, 1863-1871; Part 6.
  - General Records, 1869-1909 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 4)
    - Death Records, 1869-1909; Part 1.
    - Confirmations, 1886-1887; Part 2.
    - Confirmations, 1872-1875; Part 3.
  - General Records, 1910-1973 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 4)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Marriages, 1910-1973; Part 2.
    - Burials/Funerals, 1950-1973; Part 3.
- Baptismal Record Books, II.
  - Baptismal Records, 1869-1882 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
    - Baptisms, 1869-1882; Part 1.
    - Register, Part 2.
  - Baptismal Records, 1883-1894 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - Baptismal Records, 1895-1916 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
  - Baptismal Records, 1917-1973 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 3)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Baptisms, 1917-1973; Part 2.
- Burial/Death Record Books, III.
  - Burial/Death Records, 1869-1895 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 4)
  - Burial/Death Records, 1896-1950 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 5)
- Confirmation Record Books, IV.
  - Confirmation Records, 1876-1972 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 5)
- Zimmerman Cemetery/Birmingham Church Cemetery Records, V.
  - Burial Register, 1902-1924 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
  - Burial Register, 1924-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
  - Burial Register, 1946-1968 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
  - Burial Register, 1969-1975 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, 1874-1901 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Deed Register with Payment Ledger, Part 2.
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, 1874-1901 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, 1874-c1920 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 7)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Lot Owners, 1874-c1920; Part 2.
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, Section #2, 1958-1969 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 7)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Lot Owners, 1958-1969; Part 2.
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, Section #3, 1955-1974 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 7)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Lot Owners, 1955-1974; Part 2.
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, Section #4, 1949-1970 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 7)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Lot Owners, 1949-1970; Part 2.
  - Lot Owners/Deed Book, Section #5, 1929-1950 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 7)
    - Index, Part 1.
    - Lot Owners, 1929-1950; Part 2.
  - Interment Book, c1880-1900 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 6)
- Minute Books (including Church Constitution), VI.
  - Constitution and Minutes, 1846-1869 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 8)
  - Minutes, 1869-1889 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 8)
  - Minutes, 1889-1915 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 8-9)
    - Part 1
    - Part 2
  - Minutes, 1915-1925 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
- Congregational Histories, VII.
  - 50th Jubilee Booklet, 1896 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 8)
  - 80th Anniversary Booklet, 1926
  - Paper, c1977
  - Early Membership Lists, 1846-1869
- Financial Record Books, VIII.
  - Financial Records, 1912-1923 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1936-1941 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1939-1945 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1941-1947 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1945-1953 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1948-1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Disbursements, 1954-1958 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Disbursements, 1958-1962 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Receipts, 1954-1959 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9)
  - Financial Records, 1967 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 3, Reel 9-10)
    - Part 1
    - Part 2
    - Part 3